<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sven Schnieders</title>
    <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sven Schnieders</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2021, Sven Schnieders.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 18:32:57 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Book</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/book/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 18:32:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/book/</guid>
      <description>You can buy my book full of aphorism here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/books/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 14:58:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/books/</guid>
      <description>Here are some books I recommend, but keep in mind that you need the right book for the right person at the right time.
2020  Thus Spoke Zarathustra - Friedrich Nietzsche Our Mathematical Universe - Max Tegmark The Fountainhead - Ayn Rand Atlas Shrugged - Ayn Rand Good and Real - Gary L. Drescher Quantum Computing Since Democritus - Scott Aaronson Letters to a Young Poet - Rainer Maria Rilke Parerga and Paralipomena - Arthur Shopenhauer Stories of Your Life and Others - Ted Chiang The Last Days of Socrates - Plato Essential Bukowski: Poetry - Charles Bukowski Summerhill School - A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dressed for the special day</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/dressed/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 14:59:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/dressed/</guid>
      <description>he was wearing a tracksuit
and sneakers.
the zipper of his jacket was open.
underneath, a fancy
white shirt
with buttons.
it looked strange.
earlier that night
he had attempted suicide.
someone had stopped him
from throwing himself in front of a train.
he was neither happy
nor sad about it.
but he was drunk.
he said he put on the
fancy shirt
specifically for
his suicide attempt:
a special shirt for</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a canceled poem</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/canceled/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 14:58:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/canceled/</guid>
      <description>i log on—
everyone is raging:
a new person is being canceled.
a scientist discovered
an inconvenient truth,
or “hate fact”
as it’s now called.
a scientist,
who standing on the border
between the known
and the unknown,
tried to expand our knowledge
to make the world a better place.
looking into the abyss of the unknown,
focusing solely on the search for truth,
not bothering about anything else,
he got what one would expect:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Purpose Of Writing</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 14:24:31 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/writing/</guid>
      <description>I I, like many other people, have discovered that it is almost impossible to think seriously without writing. Writing clarifies and sharpens your thoughts in a way that is superior to merely articulating them in a conversation. It allows you to look at your ideas more objectively, almost as if they were from another person. You can then examine them and think about if what you have written down is really true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>happy walks, depressed people</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/happy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 14:56:25 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/happy/</guid>
      <description>i see them on my walks.
rushed,
depressed,
and i am so happy
i walk around smiling
without a reason.
it’s disgusting.
nobody wants to read about that shit:
happiness.
who is happy these days?
the stupid and the drunk.
the rest is depressed.
are you happy?
how stupid of you.
how insensitive,
think of all the depressed people.
you can’t just be happy
without a good reason.
happiness is shallow and simple.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humans are Special and Significant</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/humans/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 14:22:19 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/humans/</guid>
      <description>The modern scientific age has brought about a drastic change in the way we humans see ourselves. Throughout history, we considered ourselves special and important; after all, we were created in the image of God. The earth was at the center of the universe, and everything on earth was created for us (special) humans. It was a beautiful image, which unfortunately turned out to be wrong.
A Little History The picture began to crumble when Copernicus proposed his heliocentric model of our universe in 1543.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>towards heaven</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/heaven/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 14:54:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/heaven/</guid>
      <description>the last individual
in the middle of the masses.
standing neither below
nor above them.
following his own path,
his own conviction,
neither man nor god can judge
the journey he has undertaken.
every action is a consequence
of his inner core.
willing to die,
if he had to live any other way.
is he still a man,
or has he become a god?
the masses are frightened.
“neither below nor above”</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>courage</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/courage/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 14:42:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/courage/</guid>
      <description>a prison built out of freedom,
what a vicious thing.
the key, the walls,
the door, the guard—
all one,
all of the same origin.
if one tries to escape,
all hope for freedom is lost.
always running away
from the place one is searching.
if one is brave enough
to look directly at it,
the prison vanishes.
not by action,
but by truth.
after all,
there is no prison,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bitcoin - A Short Primer</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/bitcoin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 14:20:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/bitcoin/</guid>
      <description>Bitcoin is a peer-to-peer digital currency. This means there is no central entity that processes or approves your transactions—in this way it is similar to cash. As a consequence, nobody can censor your transaction, and no one can freeze—or worse, close—your “account”; you have full control over your funds. You don&amp;rsquo;t need a bank; you are your own bank.
The Bitcoin network that processes the transactions is decentralized, which is to say there is no single point of failure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modesty Kills Excellence</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/modesty/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 14:18:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/modesty/</guid>
      <description>Contrary to popular belief, I am skeptical of the benefits that modesty, as a virtue, has on our society. In particular, I am concerned that:
 By making modesty a virtue, we have made excellence a vice.
 Sure, we might have fewer arrogant idiots running around, but we also have fewer high achievers (especially in science and engineering) making huge progress.
When I talk about &amp;ldquo;high achievers&amp;rdquo; in this context, I do not mean the top 5%.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a wise man</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/wise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 14:40:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/wise/</guid>
      <description>one night,
i met a wise man.
he had just attempted suicide.
to me and my “friend” he said:
the way she looks at you,
how she makes you laugh,
that’s something special.
it’s what everyone&amp;rsquo;s looking for,
don’t lose it.
oh, how blind i was.
oh, what a wise man.
he had many plans.
our kids would go to his shows.
we had to promise it.
life happend.
no kids and no shows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>School-Think</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/school/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 14:15:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/school/</guid>
      <description>In school, problems are perfectly defined, and the possible answers are laid out, or at least the space in which the answer can be found is known. The skills needed the solve these problems have very little to do with the skills needed to solve problems in the real world. In reality, problems are only incompletely defined, and it is not known if there even exists a solution, let alone where this solution might be found.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to Ergodicity</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/ergodicity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 14:13:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/ergodicity/</guid>
      <description>The concept of ergodicity is something people get intuitively but unlearn by visiting a statistics class or completing an MBA. The distinction between ergodic and non-ergodic systems is nonetheless essential for understanding how humans act and why some “irrational” behavior or heuristic might be rational after all. It is a concept mostly used in mathematical probability theory but originated in thermodynamics.
An ergodic system is technically defined as a system that has the same behavior averaged over time as it has averaged over the space of all the system’s states.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Weirdness of Quantum Random Walks</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/quantum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 14:11:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/quantum/</guid>
      <description>Quantum mechanics is probably the most unintuitive scientific theory in the history of humankind—nothing behaves like we are used to. In this essay, we will try to get back some intuition of how to think about quantum mechanics, more specifically the quantum random walk. No worries, there are going to be no equations—this is not a scientific paper. The main purpose of this essay is to make the reader curious by showing how weird our reality is and how this knowledge might help us in the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stop Calling for a Free Market in Money</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/money/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 14:10:06 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/money/</guid>
      <description>If you prefer audio, you can listen to this essay narrated by Guy Swan on his great podcast Bitcoin Audible, episode 377.
 There are many people, coming mostly from the Austrian school of economics, who argue for a free market in money—a good example being Thorsten Polleit. (I admire his knowledge about economics, which is, unfortunately, only exceeded by his ignorance of Bitcoin.) Although I mostly agree with their reasoning and share the enthusiasm for such a free market, I cannot stop being astonished by the naivety of the idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consuming News is Harmful</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 14:07:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/news/</guid>
      <description>I recently posted this Tweet:
 No one ever got wise by reading newspapers.
 In this essay, we will explore why this is the case and I will argue that not only does news not help you to understand the world, it is actually harmful.
Note: gathering data on e.g. the Coronavirus should not be considered news consumption; looking up information is not the same as consuming news. My criticism concerns: reading daily newspapers, watching shows on e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bitcoin’s Social Antifragility</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/antifragility/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 14:03:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/antifragility/</guid>
      <description>I have argued in the past that the difficulty of changing the rules is one of the most important properties of Bitcoin. Without this security, which is in large part a consequence of decentralization, Bitcoin cannot function as a store of value. For a more detailed argumentation, I recommend reading my essay Mass Adoption of Bitcoin’s Values and this Twitter thread:
In this essay, we will take a look at why it is becoming less and less likely that these rules, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mass Adoption of Bitcoin&#39;s Values</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/vlaues/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 14:00:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/vlaues/</guid>
      <description>While the mass adoption of Bitcoin as money is a decent goal to strive for, many have already pointed out that it is far from perfect. In an ideal future, everyone not only uses Bitcoin but also holds their private keys and runs their own full node; i.e. everyone is a first-class Bitcoin citizen. Obviously, this is not realistic, but getting close to this ideal should nonetheless be the goal. There are two ways of increasing the percentage of first-class bitcoin citizens in the future; the first is technological innovation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Change and the Risk of Stagnation</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/climate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 13:56:55 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/climate/</guid>
      <description>The discussion of climate change and the potential dangers for our species has sadly been turned into a virtue-signaling contest by politicians. In this essay we will stay away from these political discussions; we will also not discuss the science behind the different climate models. Instead, we will look at something more important: the risks involved.
Precautionary Principle The problem of climate change should be viewed in the bigger context of trying to reduce the risk of global extinction (global ruin).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Rules For Reading Books</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/rules/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 14:25:40 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/rules/</guid>
      <description>A lot has been written about this topic, but I think most of those giving advice are missing the fact that there is no “right” way to read books. Instead of giving advice on what to do—via positiva—we will explore what not to do—via negativa. Advice on what not to do (or what to avoid) is not only more robust—it changes less over time—it is, in my opinion, the only advice worth giving when it comes to reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Death of Intellectual Curiosity</title>
      <link>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/curiosity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 12:55:49 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://svenschnieders.github.io/website/curiosity/</guid>
      <description>The questions we are trying to answer are as follows: why are some people curious and keep on learning throughout their lives and others do not? Why do most people stop learning after school? What happened to the quality of the education in universities?
The only information most people consume is the news and other news-like content; they rarely read books. Even if they do, they read the thriller or romance novel which is currently number one on the NYT bestseller list.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>